<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Python on Aaron Jenson</title>
    <link>https://www.aaronjenson.com/tags/python/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Python on Aaron Jenson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 21:04:24 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.aaronjenson.com/tags/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>YoshAI</title>
      <link>https://www.aaronjenson.com/posts/yoshai/yoshai/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 21:04:24 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.aaronjenson.com/posts/yoshai/yoshai/</guid>
      <description>YoshAI is a project that aims to create an AI that can play Mario Kart Wii at least as effectively as a human. It uses the Dolphin emulator as a simulation platform. At a basic level, YoshAI starts dolphin, finds the window displaying the game, and uses the pixels of the window to predict the best controls to send to dolphin. In collect mode, a user uses a gamepad to control the character and YoshAI saves the images of the game and user inputs as data to be used for training.</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;YoshAI is a project that aims to create an AI that can play Mario Kart Wii at least as effectively as a human. It uses the Dolphin emulator as a simulation platform. At a basic level, YoshAI starts dolphin, finds the window displaying the game, and uses the pixels of the window to predict the best controls to send to dolphin. In collect mode, a user uses a gamepad to control the character and YoshAI saves the images of the game and user inputs as data to be used for training. Train mode uses behavior cloning to train a convolutional neural network to copy the user&amp;rsquo;s inputs. Run mode uses the trained model to play Mario Kart. Dagger mode [TODO]&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ailofi</title>
      <link>https://www.aaronjenson.com/posts/ailofi/ailofi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.aaronjenson.com/posts/ailofi/ailofi/</guid>
      <description></description>
      <content></content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
